Avradeep Bhowmik

■ avradeep.1@gmail.com • • https://avradeep1.github.io/

Current Position

2019–Present Research Scientist, CRITEO AI LABS, Palo Alto, CA.

Managers: Zhengming Xing, S. Sathiya Keerthi

Primary I am broadly interested in machine learning, data mining, statistical inference and related fields. Interests In my education and my professional life, I have had a specific focus on machine learning and data mining in two domains- online advertising and healthcare- that included techniques like gradient boosted decision trees for bid-optimisation, recommendation systems, data reconstruction algorithms, ranking and rank aggregation, and learning with obfuscated data. In the past I have also worked on applications involving sparse modelling, image processing, language models, hierarchical learning and geometric maps for recommender systems, and submodular optimisation techniques applied to problems in operations research.

Experience

 $2019\mathrm{-Present}$ $\,$ Research Scientist , CRITEO Al LABS , Palo Alto, CA.

Managers: Zhengming Xing, S. Sathiya Keerthi

- Part of a team that developed and deployed a new model for bid-optimisation using an ensemble of gradient boosted decision trees together with coun-min-sketch features. Efforts in this project led to several A/B tests with positive results.
- Played a crucial role in model development and performed wide-ranging experimental studies on robustness and parameter tuning for optimal performance.
- Introduced multiple innovations in model design and analysis that were eventually adopted into the standard testing framework for the team in subsequent projects.
- Worked in a machine learning consultant capacity to help other teams in the company in troubleshooting problems or workshopping ideas
- Mentored several interns on their summer projects on gradient-boosted deep learning models (DNN's) and generative adversarial networks (GAN's) that are currently in the process of being developed into full research papers.
- Conducted lectures in a company-wide bootcamp that trained other employees on machine learning, and participated in reading groups on natural language processing (NLP) and reinforcement learning (RL).

Summer '17 Research Intern, CRITEO RESEARCH, Palo Alto, CA.

Manager: Suju Rajan

- Designed a novel modelling and algorithmic framework that can learn supervised generalised linear models with taxonomy information.
- Framework was designed to be compatible with missing and noisy taxonomic information, both for training and in deployment, and was able to learn accurate models even with more than half the taxonomic labels corrupted or replaced with random errors.
- In a parallel project, developed a novel predictive modelling framework for estimating individual-level cost-per-click (CPC) that can be trained using CPC data only available as daily or hourly aggregates over clickstreams.
- Framework was generalised to incorporate GLMs and demonstrated applicability to domains beyond online advertising

Summer '16 Research Intern, Verizon Labs, Palo Alto, CA.

Manager: Santanu Das

- Designed feature selection algorithms for scalable time series recommendation and extracting relevant information from customer purchase history to learn top ranked items for future purchase interest.
- Technique thus developed reduced the complexity of training by 92% with almost no loss in accuracy and provided actionable marketing insights on relevant customer information for future promotional campaigns

Summer '16 Research Intern, YAHOO RESEARCH, Palo Alto, CA.

Manager: Suju Rajan

- Developed new modelling paradigms and algorithms for high dimensional sparse factor embeddings of user and item features for real time search and recommendation.
- Designed a novel framework that used geometric mapping schemata between a high dimensional permutation space to tiles on a tessellated unit sphere to obtain sparse parameters for factorisation models.
- Empirical tests on real datasets found the technique to outperform state-of-the-art tree-based or hashing techniques in both speed and accuracy

CGPA: 3.90/4.00.

CGPA: 9.43/10.00.

Education

MS-PhD The University of Texas at Austin, USA,

2013-2018 Advisor: Prof. Joydeep Ghosh,

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering.

o PhD. ECE 2016-2018. \circ MS, ECE 2013–2016.

B. Tech Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, India,

2009-2013 Department of Electrical Engineering.

PhD Thesis

Dissertation Learning from Aggregated Data

Data aggregation is a ubiquitous feature in modern data-driven applications due to concerns like privacy, robustness and scalability. However, most existing machine learning algorithms are only designed to work with data at the individual granular level. The focus of my dissertation is to bridge this gap and design algorithms and modelling frameworks that have strong predictive performance at the individual level but can be trained with data only available as aggregates. A variety of both linear and non-linear models are studied and extended to the aggregated data setting using techniques from diverse areas like compressed sensing and Fourier analysis. The methods thus developed in the thesis are applied to domains like healthcare, climate science, ecological studies, etc. where data is frequently available only in a naturally aggregated aggregated form.

Selected Special Topics in Machine Learning, Large Scale Optimisation, Statistical Relational Learning, Infor-Coursework mation Theory, Graphical Models, Approximation Algorithms, Time Series and Dynamic Models, Monte Carlo Methods, Probability and Stochastic Processes, Genomic Signal Processing, Program Derivation, Topics in Automata and Logic

Publications

submitted A Bhowmik, J Ghosh, O Koyejo "SLAGG: An Aggregation Framework for Predictive Modelling with Non-Retention Constraints for Sensitive Data", (currently under review)

submitted A Bhowmik, Z Xing, S Rajan, "A General Framework for Learning with Taxonomy", (currently under review)

- 2019 A Bhowmik, M Chen, Z Xing, S Rajan, "EsTIMAGG: A Learning Framework for Groupwise Aggregated Data", In Proceedings of the 2019 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining (SDM), Calgary, Alberta, Canada, May 2-4, 2019
- 2017 A Bhowmik, J Ghosh, O Koyejo, "Frequency Domain Predictive Modelling with Aggregated Data", Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2017, Fort Lauderdale, Florida, USA, April 20-22, 2017
- 2017 A Bhowmik, J Ghosh, "LETOR Methods for Unsupervised Rank Aggregation", Proceedings of the 26th International World Wide Web Conference (WWW) 2017, Perth, Australia, April 3-7, 2017

- 2016 **A Bhowmik**, J Ghosh, O Koyejo, "Sparse Parameter Recovery from Aggregated Data", Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2016, New York City, NY, USA, June 19-24, 2016
- 2016 **A Bhowmik**, N Liu, E Zhong, B N Bhaskar, S Rajan, "Geometry Aware Mappings for High Dimensional Sparse Factors", Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2016, Cadiz, Spain, May 9-11, 2016
- 2015 **A Bhowmik**, J Ghosh, O Koyejo, "Generalized Linear Models for Aggregated Data", Proceedings of the 18th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics, (AISTATS) 2015, San Diego, California, USA, May 9-12, 2015, (Oral presentation)
- 2014 **A Bhowmik**, V Borkar, D Garg, M Pallan, "Submodularity in the Team Formation Problem", Proceedings of the 2014 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining (SDM), Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, April 24-26, 2014

Research Experience

2013–2018 The University of Texas Austin, USA, Graduate Research Assistant.

Worked on multiple NSF and industry funded projects.

Supervisor: Dr. Joydeep Ghosh

- Fourier analysis for linear modelling with non-uniform spatio-temporally aggregated data
- Sparse linear estimation and parameter recovery with group-wise aggregates
- Generalised linear modelling with histogram aggregation
- Monotone Retargeting and LETOR methods for rank aggregation with object features

2012–2013 Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Bombay, *India*, Undergraduate Research.

Supervisor: Dr. Vivek Borkar

- Sub-modular formulation and analysis of ad-hoc team formation problem in social networks (collaboration with Dr. Dinesh Garg, IBM Research)
- Adaptive clustering with the weighted majority algorithm for cold-start recommendation systems (collaboration with Dr. Onkar Dabeer, Qualcomm Research)

Summer '12 Institute of Science and Technology (IST), Austria, Visiting Researcher.

Supervisor: Dr. Christoph Lampert

- Randomised hashing techniques for clustering images in a large database
- Designing new similarity metrics for efficient neighbourhood graph construction

Awards and Honors

- -Recipient of the George J. Heuer, Jr. Ph.D. Endowed Graduate Fellowship for year 2013
- -Qualified IIT JEE with an All India Rank of 34 (top 0.008%) and rank 1 in the IIT Guwahati Zone
- -All India Rank of 212 (top 0.0002%) and State rank 1 in AIEEE year 2009
- -6th rank in the state (top 0.006%) in WBJEE examination 2009

Programming

Python (primary), R, Matlab, PyTorch, TensorFlow, basic experience in Scala, PySpark, bash, Perl, C++, etc.

Academic Service

Reviewer:

NeurIPS 2019, IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering, Journal of Ecological Modelling, Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering, IEEE Access

PC Member:

ACM International Conference on the World Wide Web 2017

Miscellaneous

Volunteer for National Service Scheme (NSS) for the year $2009\hbox{--}2010$ Member of the organising committee for TechFest 2010 at IIT Bombay

References

Available upon request